Guide to the Lester Wunderman Papers, 1946-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lester Wunderman papers 1946-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wunderman, Lester
60 linear feet Extent: 42000 Items
Lester Wunderman is an advertising executive primarily in the direct marketing industry, founder of an agency in his name now a subsidiary of Young & Rubicam, and a noted collector of Dogon (Mali) art works. The Lester Wunderman Papers span the years 1946-2010 and include writings, speeches, correspondence, reports, photographs, audiocassettes, videocassettes, 16mm films, and other materials relating to Wunderman's career in direct marketing and direct-mail advertising, his work on Boards of Directors and Trustees, and as a consultant. Included are drafts, proofs and correspondence relating to Wunderman's 1996 book Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay. Advertising agencies represented in the collection include Caspar Pinsker, Maxwell Sackheim, Wunderman Cato Johnson, Wunderman Ricotta & Kline and Young & Rubicam. Also included are correspondence, photographs, negatives and other materials relating to Wunderman's collection of Dogon (Mali) art works, carvings and sculptures, and their use in museum exhibits, catalogs and books on African art. Firms and institutions represented in the collection include American Express, Children's Television Workshop (Sesame Street, Electric Company), Columbia House record club, Ford (including Lincoln-Mercury and Merkur), IBM, Jackson & Perkins mail order nursery, Mitchell Madison Group, Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.), National Observer Correspondence Schools (Famous Artists School, Famous Writers School) and Time, Inc. magazines. Languages present include Spanish, French, Danish, German and Japanese, and have not been translated into English. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.01417
Language: Material in English French, Spanish, Danish, German, Japanese
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Unpublished materials are closed to non-Wunderman researchers for 15 years from the date of creation.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lester Wunderman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1920 June 22 Born, New York, N.Y.
1939 Co-founder, with brother Irving, Coronet Advertising Service
1942-1947 Vice President, Caspar Pinsker Advertising Agency
1947 Joined Maxwell Sackheim & Co. advertising agency; eventually promoted to Executive Vice President
1958 President and Founder, Wunderman Ricotta & Kline (WRK)
1961 Oct. 1 Speech to Hundred Million Club (precursor to Direct Marketing Club of New York); first documented use of the term direct marketing in a speech by Wunderman
1967 Mail Order Man of the Year, Advertising Club of New York MIT speech, elaboration of the direct marketing concept before the American Marketing Association; speech later read into the Congressional Record
1973 WRK merged with Young & Rubicam
1973-1976 Travels to Africa; photography of Dogon life and sculpture
1977 Chairman, WRK
1981 Frontiers of Direct Marketing published
1982 Direct Marketer of the Year, Direct Marketing Day in New York
Circa 1982-1989 Chairman, Visiting Committee of the Arts of Africa, Oceania and the Americas, Metropolitan Museum of Art
1983 Direct Marketing Association Hall of Fame
1984 Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters, Brooklyn College, City University of New York
1985 Focus Award, Montreux Symposium of Direct Marketing
Circa 1986-1992 Trustee, Children's Television Workshop
1987 WRK name change to Wunderman Worldwide
1988 Special Exhibition of Wunderman's Dogon art collection, Metropolitan Museum of Art, N.Y., and the Louvre, Paris
1992 Wunderman Worldwide merger with Cato Johnson to form Wunderman Cato Johnson
1994 Edward N. Mayer, Jr. Award for Educational Leadership, Direct Marketing Educational Foundation
1996 Wunderman LLC consulting firm Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay published
1997 Lifetime Achievement Award, Direct Marketing Day in New York
1998 Advertising Hall of Fame
1998 Retired from Wunderman Cato Johnson
2001 Wunderman Cato Johnson renamed Wunderman, NY; Wunderman named Chairman Emeritus
2004 Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay, second edition, published
2010 Chairman Emeritus, Visiting Committee, Rockefeller Wing at The Metropolitan Museum of Art, N.Y.
In addition, Wunderman has been involved in a range of professional and personal activities:
Education: Adjunct Professor of Marketing, Columbia University School for Continuing Education; Visiting Clinical Professor of Direct Marketing, School for Continuing Education, New York University; Chairman, Executive Committee, Center for Direct Marketing, New York University; Editorial Review Board, Journal of Direct Marketing, Medill School of Journalism, Northwestern University; Lectured on direct marketing, primitive art, communications and advertising. Attended New York University, City University of New York, Brooklyn College, Columbia University.
Professional organizations: Director, The Advertising Council; Board of Directors, Direct Marketing Association; Secretary/Treasurer, American Association of Advertising Agencies; Founding Chairman, DMA International Strategic Forum on Direct Marketing; Director, The Marketing Consortium; Founder, Lester Wunderman Instituut, Amsterdam. Co-Founder (with Cornell Capa and Jacqueline Kennedy), International Center of Photography
Specialist in Dogon (Mali) art: Assembled the largest privately held collection of Dogon art, which toured several museums before a large portion of the collection was donated to the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Louvre; the collection formed the illustrations on several books on African art.
Humanitarian work: Administrative Council, UNESCO International Fund for the Promotion of Culture; Co-Chairman, Friends of Leopold Senghor Foundation; President, Wunderman Foundation, which funds research in developing regions. Member, UNICEF, Paris.
Collection Overview
The Lester Wunderman Papers span the years 1946-2010 and include writings, speeches, correspondence, reports, photographs, audiocassettes, videocassettes, 16mm films, and other materials relating to Wunderman's career in direct marketing and direct-mail advertising, his work on Boards of Directors and Trustees, and as a consultant. Included are drafts, proofs and correspondence relating to Wunderman's 1996 book Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay. Advertising agencies represented in the collection include Caspar Pinsker, Maxwell Sackheim, Wunderman Cato Johnson, Wunderman Ricotta & Kline and Young & Rubicam. Also included are correspondence, photographs, negatives and other materials relating to Wunderman's collection of Dogon (Mali) art works, carvings and sculptures, and their use in museum exhibits, catalogs and books on African art. Firms and institutions represented in the collection include American Express, Children's Television Workshop (Sesame Street, Electric Company), Columbia House record club, Ford (including Lincoln-Mercury and Merkur), IBM, Jackson & Perkins mail order nursery, Mitchell Madison Group, Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.), National Observer Correspondence Schools (Famous Artists School, Famous Writers School) and Time, Inc. magazines. Languages present include Spanish, French, Danish, German and Japanese, and have not been translated into English.
Collection Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into six series: Administrative Files; Speeches; Writings; Memorabilia; Oversize Materials; and Audiovisual Materials. Administrative Files include biographical materials as well as materials relating to awards, travel, Wunderman's activities as a consultant and member of the Boards of Directors and Trustees of various institutions, publicity notices and samples of direct marketing items. Speeches include typed and hand-written drafts of speeches given by Wunderman, along with alternate versions and correspondence relating to speaking engagements. Writings includes drafts, proofs and published articles, notes and correspondence, as well as a Book File related to Wunderman's book Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay. Memorabilia includes plaques, trophies, certificates and other commemorative items. Oversize Materials comprise large-format items removed from previous series. Their logical location is noted in the Detailed Description with entries in square brackets, cross referenced to their physical location in this Series. Audiovisual Materials include audiocassettes, videocassettes and films. Materials not in English have not been translated. Where possible, original folder titles have been retained.
Subject Headings
Wunderman, Lester; Sackheim, Maxwell, 1890-; Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay.; American Express Company; Children's Television Workshop; Columbia House (Firm); Famous Writers School; Famous Artists School (Westport, Conn.); Ford Motor Company. Lincoln-Mercury Division; International Business Machines Corporation; Jackson & Perkins Co; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Time, Inc.; Young & Rubicam; Advertising; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- United States; Advertising, Direct-mail; Advertising, Direct-mail -- History; Advertising, Direct-mail -- United States; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Direct marketing; Direct marketing -- History; Direct marketing -- United States; Art, African; Art, Dogon; Dogon (African people); Museum exhibits; African sculpture styles; Carvings (visual work); Sculpture (visual work); Dogon; Negatives; Photographs; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; 16mm; 35mm; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Separated Material
The following digital media have been removed from the collection. Paper versions exist in the collection.
Disk 1: Writings--Drafts and Proofs--Appendix materials. Undated. Format: SyQuest 88mb Removable Cartridge.
Disk 2-3. Business-to-Business Direct Marketing. 1982. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 4. DMA speech. 1983 Mar. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 5-6. Direct Marketing Day in New York. 1983. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 7-8. DMA Miami speech. 1983. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 9-10. Semaine Française du Marketing Direct. 1984. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 11-13. Frontiers of Direct Marketing II. 1984 May. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 14. Direct Marketing, entry in International Encyclopedia of Communications. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 15. Media International article. Undated. Format: 5.25 floppy
Disk 16. Australia speech. 1985. Format: 5.25 floppy
The following books have been removed from the collection to be cataloged separately:
Atkinson, J. Edward, Ed. 1971. Black Dimensions in Contemporary American Art. New York: Plume.
Barty-King, Hugh. 1980. The AA: A History of the First 75 Years of the Au tomobile Association. Basingstoke: Automobile Association.
Bloch, Philippe et al. 1986. Service Compris. L'Expansion/Hachette.
Cornell, James Jr. 1964. The People Get the Credit: The First One Hundred Years of The Spiegel Story. Spiegel, Inc.
David, Michel. 1986. La vente par correspondence. Paris: Chotard et Associés Editeurs.
Nichols, Lee, Ed. 1981. Conversations with African Writers. Washington, D.C.: Voice of America.
Nichols, Lee, Ed. 1982. Science in Africa: Interviews with African Scientists. Washington, D.C.: Voice of America.
Shipley, Joseph T. 1945. Dictionary of Word Origins 2nd Edition. New York: Philosophical Library.
Toffler, Alvin. 1985. The Adaptive Corporation. New York: McGraw-Hill.
Yankelovich, Skelly and White. 1987. Direct Marketing in the Year 2000.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection
Arlie R. Slabaugh Collection of Direct Mail Literature
Charles McKinney Papers
Colored Mail Order Corporation of America records
J. Walter Thompson Company. Bertram Metter Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Ronald B. Kaatz Papers
John Benjamin Harris Papers
Kensinger Jones Papers
Leo Bogart Papers
McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Vertical File
Sears, Roebuck and Company Catalog Collection.
Sheldon B. Sosna Papers
Superior Match Company matchbook advertising catalog and sales representative's forms
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Files, 1952-1999 and undated, (17 boxes)
  Arranged into subseries General Files; Accounts; Children's Television Workshop; Dogon Art; Meetings and Travel; Metropolitan Museum of Art; Printed Materials; Publicity; and Samples of Direct Marketing Items. Where possible, original folder titles have been retained. Materials in other languages have not been translated into English. Large-format items have been removed to Oversize Materials and their logical location noted in the Description by a note or an entry enclosed in square brackets.
  Restrictions on Access: Unpublished materials are closed to non-Wunderman researchers for 15 years from the date of creation.
  - General Files, 1958-1999
    - Awards (Box 1)
      - Direct Marketing Education Foundation, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Echo Awards, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Honorary degree, Brooklyn College, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 1)
        [Includes copy of Green, Janice S. et al. 1985. Opportunity in Adversity: How Colleges Can Succeed in Hard Times. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass. Inscribed to Wunderman from Brooklyn College President Robert Hess.]
      - Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Silver Apple Awards, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Biographical
      - Biographical sketches, 1958-1998, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - Photographs, 1961-1999, (7 folders; 4 folders removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Adweek Agency Report, 1985 (Box 1)
      - [Christmas card design layout, undated: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10] (Box 1)
      - European Managers Meeting, 1976 (Box 1)
      - New York University correspondence, 1993 (Box 1)
      - New York University Synectics Think Tank, The Future of Marketing, 1992 (Box 1)
      - Review comments, Journal of Consumer Marketing article (undisclosed author), 1982 (Box 1)
      - Young & Rubicam Marketing Managers Survey, Business-to-Business marketing, 1983 (Box 1)
  - General Files--Restricted Items, 1995-1999
    [Unpublished materials are closed to non-Wunderman Cato Johnson staff for 15 years from the date of creation.]
    - Barrington Hills Relationship Technologies, 1995-1998, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Direct Marketing Association
      - Leaders Forum, 1998 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Electronic Schoolhouse, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Henry Grunewald, Soul magazine, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Lenny Barshack correspondence, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Mitchell Madison Group
      - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 2)
      - Marketing conference, 1999 (Box 2)
      - Murray Bowes (MBI)/Honda, 1998 (Box 2)
      - Procter & Gamble, 1998 (Box 2)
      - Selected marketing lab decks, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Presentation to Estée Lauder, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Sam Zell/Equity Group, 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - TED (Technology, Entertainment, Design) Conferences, 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Young & Rubicam, Peter Georgescu, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - Accounts, 1963-1972
    - WBAI, 1963-1966 (Box 4)
    - McGovern-Shriver campaign, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Ralph Stevens contest (Famous Writers School), 1968 (Box 4)
  - Children's Television Workshop, 1986-1992
    - Board of Trustees, 1986-1989, (8 folders) (Box 5)
    - Board of Trustees, 1989-1992, (9 folders) (Box 6)
    - Board of Trustees, 1992, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Literacy project, circa 1989, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Orientation materials, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Proposal for Sesame Street in the Soviet Union, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Sesame Street Preschool Education Program (PEP) Initiative, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Sesame Street research bibliography, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Dogon Art, 1972-1990 and undated
    - African Arts, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
    - Art of the Dogon: Selections from the Lester Wunderman Collection, 1988 (Box 8)
    - [Article in Life, 1966 June 3: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV1] (Box 8)
    - Dogon Sculpture article, Art News, 1973 Sept. (Box 8)
    - [Dogon World children's catalog, undated: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10] (Box 8)
    - Manhattan, Inc., 1988 Apr. (Box 8)
    - National Geographic, 1990 Oct. (Box 8)
    - New Acquisitions in the Wunderman Collection, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Pieces no longer part of the Wunderman collection (photograph album), 1977, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Primitivism in 20th Century Art (Museum of Modern Art), 1985 (Box 8)
    - [Scrapbook, 1973-1975: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV1] (Box 8)
    - Photographs (Box 9)
      - [African art, undated: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10] (Box 9)
      - Dogon dancers (color prints), undated (Box 9)
      - Dogon people and villages, undated (Box 9)
      - Dogon sculpture, circa 1973 (Box 9)
      - [Dogon sculpture, undated: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10] (Box 9)
      - Dogon sculpture, Brooklyn Museum exhibit, undated (Box 9)
      - Environmental shots of Dogon in Mali, undated (Box 9)
      - Wunderman Dogon collection
        - Items not in Laude catalog, undated (Box 9)
        - Jean Laude catalog items, (6 folders) (Box 9)
        - Prints returned from Viking, used in Laude, Art of the Dogon, undated, (2 folders; one folder removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10) (Box 9)
      - Wunderman in Africa, undated, (3 folders; one folder removed to Oversize Materials Box OV10) (Box 9)
    - Negatives, undated, (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - Meetings and Travel, 1969, 1996-1999
    Includes meeting agendas, correspondence, travel itineraries and printed materials.
    - [Lonsdale Wunderman (London), 1969 Mar. 6: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV1] (Box 10)
  - Meetings and Travel, 1996-1999 [Restricted]
    - Asian Direct Marketing Symposium, 1997, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Canadian Direct Marketing Association conference, Toronto, 1997 (Box 11)
    - Direct Marketing Association conference, Chicago, 1997 (Box 11)
    - International Managers Meeting, Baden-Baden, 1997 (Box 11)
    - London Direct Marketing Association conference, 1997, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Newell Conference, 1996-1997, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Oracle Conference, 1999, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Universal Postal Conference, Beijing, 1999, (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1982-1989
    - General, 1982-1985, (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - Dogon show, 1986-1988, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Museum Guide Publications, Inc., 1988 (Box 13)
    - Primitive Wing, 1982, (3 folders; one folder removed to Oversize Materials Box OV1) (Box 13)
    - Task Force (Box 14)
      - General, 1987-1989, (3 folders) (Box 14)
      - Survey of King Tut show, 1987 (Box 14)
      - Survey of Vatican show, 1987 (Box 14)
  - Printed Materials, 1952-1989
    - 5th International Direct Marketing and Mail Order Symposium, 1973 (Box 15)
    - 6th International Direct Marketing and Mail Order Symposium, 1974 (Box 15)
    - [Flair, 1950 Apr., Aug.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV1] (Box 15)
    - Montreux Symposium, 1988 (Box 15)
    - [Scrapbooks of newspaper reprints, Ev'ry Month, 1897 Apr. 1, and 1961 reprint of 1861 Harper's Weekly: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV2], (2 scrapbooks) (Box 15)
    - Service et Client, circa 1988 (Box 15)
    - Seven Deadly Advertising Mistakes, Maxwell Sackheim & Co., 1952 (Box 15)
    - The Truth About Direct Marketing, 1988 (Box 15)
    - Un Entreprise Aujourd'hui--Avon, Dominique Xardel, circa 1983 (Box 15)
    - Usage Trends in the European Direct Mail Market, 1989 (Box 15)
    - Venture Funding and High Technology in France, Howard Associates, 1987 (Box 15)
  - Publicity, 1964-2010
    - Articles
      - Advertising Age, 1966-1967 (Box 16)
      - [Advertising Age, 1993 Oct.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - Adweek, Wunderman Predicts First $1 Billion Direct Shop, by Maria Fisher, 1983 Feb. 21 (Box 16)
      - [Anuncios (Spain), 1995 June: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - [Børsen (Denmark), 1996 Jan.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - Business Week, Survival in Direct Marketing, 1978 Oct. (Box 16)
      - [Campaña (Spain), 1995 June: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - Chicago Tribune/New York Times, 1978, (2 folders; one folder removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3) (Box 16)
      - [Dentsu Journal/Telemarketing Journal (Japan), 1994 Apr.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - [Direct (book excerpt), 1996 Nov.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - [Direct, 1998 Mar.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - [Direct, 1999 Feb.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV3] (Box 16)
      - [Direktmarketing (Germany), 1990: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - Direktwerbung und Verkaufsförderung, Mail Order--die kommende Revolution im Marketing (article in German), 1967 July (Box 16)
      - [DM News, 1994 May 9: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - [Economie (Belgium), 1996 May: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - Economist, Direct Hit, 1999 Jan. 9 (Box 16)
      - Estrategias, Las profecias de Lester Wunderman (article in Spanish), 1995 July 14 (Box 16)
      - [Financial Times, 1990 Apr.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - Fortune, There's a Lot of Satisfaction (Guaranteed) in Direct Marketing, by Walter McQuade, 1980 apr. 21 (Box 16)
      - IMPress (Japan; article in Japanese), 1997 (Box 16)
      - [IP Mark (Spain), 1995 June: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - Japan Marketing Journal (article in Japanese), 1994 (Box 16)
      - [La Vanguardia (Spain), 1995 Aug.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - [Life cover article Mail Order Man of the Year, 1967 Mar. 3: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - [Marketing Magazine (Canada), 1994 Nov.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - [Marketing Magazine (Canada), 1997 Nov.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - MIT speech read into Congressional Record, 1967 (Box 16)
      - New Yorker, A Critic at Large: The Spin Myth, 1998 July 6 (Box 16)
      - Werben und Verkaufen, Kein Spiel für Anfänger (article in German), 1994 Apr. 8 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous articles and notices, 1985 (Box 16)
    - Interviews
      - Action Commerciale (France), 1995 Nov. (Box 16)
      - Adweek special direct marketing section, 2010 (Box 16)
      - Alternativas de Marketing (Spain), 1992 Jan. (Box 16)
      - Boardroom, 2000 Apr. (Box 16)
      - Direct Marketing, 1986 Mar. (Box 16)
      - Direct Marketing News (France), 1995 Oct. 19 (Box 16)
      - [Direct Marketing News, 1995 Dec.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - [Direct Marketing News, 1996 Jan.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)
      - Direct Response, 1997 Nov. (Box 16)
      - [DM News, 1996 Feb.: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV4] (Box 16)